Jacob Sayles

Vancouver, BC Canada - cv@jacobsayles.com - CA: 604.240.2780 - US: 206.779.9709

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a creative and entrepreneurial technologist with over 20 years of experience and a history of innovative ideas, well executed projects, and management of diverse teams. In 2007, I recognized the growing trend and lack of support structures in place for independent and remote workers and opened Office Nomads, the first coworking space in Seattle. To support this business and others like it, I wrote Nadine, the first open source coworking platform, and founded Open Coworking, a non-profit dedicated to supporting the Coworking Movement. I am currently a partner at Kanawha Design Studio, a consulting firm that supports small and large collaborative spaces with business planning, operations, community development, IT infrastructure, and the many uses of technology to support their memberships and communities.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Demonstrated management skills working with diverse teams of developers, analysts and contractors
- Creative problem-solving skills and the ability to take projects through to completion under strict timelines and parameters
- Ability to hone larger organizational goals into practical plans of action
- Agile, hands-on style with iterative and collaborative development and an emphasis on simplicity and maintainability
- Proven experience in all phases of the software development life cycle: requirements gathering, developing technical specifications, architecture, design, user experience, implementation, testing and maintenance
- A deep and personal commitment to creating and being part of rich, dynamic communities

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

The Evergreen State College, Olympia, WA - Computer Science, Bachelor of Science	1995 - 1997
Western Washington University, Fairhaven College, Bellingham, WA	1994 - 1995
JBoss for Java Developers, Learning Patterns, Portland, OR	2006
PFSense Firewall Certification, Netgate, Austin, TX	2017

TECHNOLOGIES

Python (2.7, 3.7), Django (1.11, 2.1), 2to3, Docker, Vagrant, VMWare, AWS, Zabbix, Apache, Nginx, Drupal, WordPress, PHP, LAMP, C++, Java, J2EE, EJB, JSP, Servlets, Ant, JBoss, Tomcat, MARC, marc4j, SQL, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server, Oracle, PostgreSQL, JavaScript, jQuery, CSS, HTML, XML, JSON, YAML, REST, Jekyll, LDAP, UNIX, Linux, FreeBSD, OpenBSD, PFSense, CVS, SVN, Git, Arduino, Raspberry Pi, vi

EXPERIENCE

Technical Director
Kanawha Design Studio, Vancouver, BC/Seattle, WA

Jul 2016 - Present
kanawha.design

Kanawha Design is a consulting firm that provides business, technology and design services to collaborative spaces. I oversee the technology and operations of the firm as well as many of our consultation projects. My contributions to clients include planning, budgeting, implementation and overall operational management of business systems and technologies.

- Watch emerging trends and keep up to date on the latest technology
- Oversee contractors for projects, including designers, analysts, admins and developers
- Manage multiple projects with competing deadlines and priorities
- Maintain business to business and business to client relationships
- Experiment with different ways to utilize technology in a variety of small to large organizations
- Analyze technical needs of clients in order to help them adjust projects, expectations, and budgets accordingly
- Work with clients to develop business strategies, cashflow analysis, organizational structures, and operation plans
- Design systems and strategies to meet client goals and either provide support for or execute implementation

Co-Founder/Director of Technology Office Nomads, Seattle WA

Apr 2007 - present officenomads.com

Office Nomads is a coworking community dedicated to cultivating a dynamic, creative and collaborative environment for Seattle's nomadic workforce. Founded on the principle that by working together we can accomplish more than we could alone, we are proving you can maintain individuality without isolation.

- Founded a coworking space by cultivating a dynamic community
- Managed all aspects of business including bookkeeping, payroll, budgeting, profit and loss, and administration
- Wrote an open source member management application used for billing, reporting, and member engagement using Python Django (nadineproject.org)
- Designed, built, and integrated systems for operations including accounting (Xero), payment processing, and IT (network, firewall, phones, internet)
- Formed an alliance with other Seattle area collaborative spaces to promote the Coworking Movement locally (collaborativespaces.org)
- Featured in many national publications including Entrepreneur magazine, The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, Fortune Small Business, Seattle magazine, King 5 News, Q13 Fox News, and Seattle Metropolitan magazine (2008 Hottest Companies in Seattle)

Director of Technology The 312 Main Project, Vancouver BC

Mar 2016 - Dec 2018

312main.ca

312 Main is a Global Centre for Social and Economic Innovation in Vancouver. Formerly the Vancouver Police Headquarters, the 105,000 sf concrete 1950's building was renovated to house socially oriented organizations, entrepreneurs, and artists. I was recruited to design and build out all of the technology systems, customize and implement the open source coworking software and build and lead the Technology Department. Working with the project from construction through the start of the business, I designed and implemented all of the essential technology systems.

- Provided leadership and deep involvement in conversion of a 105,000 sf concrete police station into an open work and meeting space for modern organizations
- Designed and managed the technical and security systems during the construction phase
- Worked closely with the project architects, general contractor, trades and other associated professionals
- Designed and oversaw installation all systems, including a fibre backbone, 5 brocade switch stacks, ≈1000 ethernet ports, and ruckus wireless system with 22 access points
- Conceived and developed access control and security systems for the building
- Designed and built a cost effective and efficient network for multiple organizations and users, including a wireless network strategy, a VLAN strategy, redundant firewalls and a network security
- Aided in developing an operations plan, staffing plan and implementation schedule for the coworking and event spaces.
- Helped to manage the transition from construction phase through occupancy
- Developed and implemented an A/V plan for the building to house multiple organizations and users, including event and stage PA and lighting equipment, printers and meeting room and classroom conferencing equipment
- Created job descriptions for a 4-person technology department, and, vetted, hired, and trained the team
- Customized the open source coworking software according to the needs of the organization and managed the developers

Founder/Executive Director Open Coworking, Seattle WA

Jan 2012 - Dec 2015 opencoworking.org

The community behind the international Coworking Movement collaborates using a variety of tools from a mailing list with over 7500 users, Slack channel, a shared wiki, and programs such as the Coworking Visa. As a core maintainer I established this non-profit organization to take on the ongoing maintenance and promotion of these resources and coordinate the volunteer efforts from around the world.

- Established a non-profit to help facilitate collaboration between coworking spaces around the world
- Built and managed a distributed organizational structure and an international team consisting of volunteers and staff members of coworking and collaborative spaces
- Maintained shared resources and a large volume of continuously incoming content.
- Conducted an international fundraising campaign

Senior Developer/Technical Lead

Serials Solutions, Seattle WA

Dec 2002 - Jan 2010 proquest.com

- Designed and implemented a data import/maintenance/transformation web application suite using JBoss, MySQL, and SQL Server
- Led a team of Java developers, database engineers, and program managers to maintain system uptime and implement new features
- Facilitated communication and coordination across departments
- Developed high availability, multi-tier, XML search engine with XSL transformation using Apache Tomcat and MySQL
- Built fully decoupled log queuing and overflow management system utilized by three high-traffic enterprise applications
- Constructed search statistics reporting and graphing utilities using Java Applets and Servlets

Vice President of Technology

Mar 2007 - Apr 2007

Clickeats.com, Seattle WA

clickeats.com

- Gathered and led development efforts into cohesive, comprehensive technology plan to deliver value for the company and bring the product to market
- Managed Java development contractors

Web Application Developer

Oct 2000 - Oct 2001

Healthetech, Seattle, WA

- Built a multi-tier J2EE personal fitness application using BEA WebLogic
- Integrated front-end HTML to back-end EJB and Oracle database

Wireless Application Developer (contract)

Sep 2000 - Oct 2000

Wireless Vision, Munich, Germany

- Developed WAP fitness application for wireless phones using Java Servlets
- Built and secured OpenBSD firewall and Apache/Tomcat web server
- Trained and supported users in application usage and operation
- Installed and maintained Solaris servers for development department

Electronic Commerce Systems Developer

Mar 1999 - Aug 2000

Usedbooks.com, Seattle, WA

usedbooks.com

- Built E-commerce framework using Cold Fusion on IIS
- Created Java Servlet search engine for external metadata search web sites
- Produced and maintained internal tools for accounting, customer service and reporting
- Created and secured office e-mail, printing, and network infrastructure using Linux

Integration Programmer

May 1998 - Mar 1999

Eden Systems, Seattle, WA

- Data migration of government accounting data into Informix-4GL applications
- Customized accounting applications to meet customer requirements
- Updated systems for Y2K compliance

VOLUNTEERING AND AFFILIATIONS

Seattle Mini Maker Faire

Coworking Europe (Keynote Speaker)

Global Coworking Unconference Conference - US

Global Coworking Unconference Conference - Canada

PyCascades Python Conference

SEGD/Vancouver Design Week

Seattle Subway

Cascadia Rail

Open Lunar Foundation

Seattle Collaborative Space Alliance

Coworking BC Society

Vancouver Hack Society

Metrix Create Space

Embassy Network and Red Victorian Coliving Hotel

District Commons